Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and what we
are going to be looking at today
is electromagnetic radiation.
Uh, we are going to be trying to
understand the basic concepts of the
wave, how this can carry energy that
will excite different atoms, and be
able to promote electrons up and down
energy levels, which will help us
be able to see how these different
elements behave when they're excited.
Um, it also is how energy gets
transported in a lot of different
chemical reactions as well when
they get heated up and cool down.
Uh, so what, what exactly are
we going to be looking at as
we're moving through this, right?
The first thing you're going to see
is like, oh, these look really cool.
These are all kinds of different lights.
And that's the thing, right?
They're all different
fluorescent processes.
What is this?
It's all emission, or
phosphorescence, fluorescence.
How can radiation be
seen and observed, right?
These are all visible forms of
light that are being given off
that can be observed via the eyes.
What's causing that?
Well, it's all about the
relaxation of electrons.
So when an electron gets excited,
meaning it absorbed a bunch of energy,
it's kind of vibrating around and then
it goes up to a higher energy level.
Now, when it comes back down, it
can emit light in order to relax.
So it's how it de stresses itself.
So all these are how electrons
can de stress, and we can see all
kinds of cool effects as a result.
Meaning that light and matter are
inter, are intimately connected.
All these are made of matter,
and they all emit light.
So they're related.
So this is, this was a problem
that really tried and baffled the
physics community for centuries,
is how they could describe this.
Because, essentially, around the,
around the year 1899, around 1900,
physics was able to explain everything.
They thought they had it all figured
out, but the thing was, is one thing
that it could not explain was how
light and matter interacted when
it came down to the atomic level.
Everything broke and that's what we're
going to be trying to look at in this
video and trying to understand is
what the nature of light is all about.
Let's take a look as we move forward.
All
comes down from is the nature of light
is all about electromagnetic radiation.
Now that word electro, that means that
there's an electric field, regionic
space that's electrically charged.
And then there's a magnetic field
where we have magnetic forces.
Meaning that particles that are
subatomic particles that have
positive and negative charges,
they're going to be affected by these.
Just like what we've seen how they
discovered all the different subatomic
particles, electromagnetic radiation
can affect all these different things.
So with electromagnetic radiation,
how exactly does it work?
Well, it's all about oscillating motion.
If you look really closely, you can see
that the waves here, there's two of them
that are perpendicular, like a cross.
And you see that they're both
oscillating towards you, right?
The red one up there is all,
is essentially showing the
magnetic field and the blue one
is showing the electric field.
They are perpendicular and
they're both oscillating extremely
fast when it's real time.
Now, how fast are we talking?
All electromagnetic radiation,
it moves at the speed of light.
which is 2.
998 times 10 to the 8th
power meters per second.
So we are talking very, very quick and
very, very fast as these are all moving.
So when these are moving, we got to
understand exactly how does the anatomy of
the wave look and how can we represent it.
So the first thing is, is seeing that,
okay, every wave, it's oscillating motion.
And we can label all those different
individual parts that we have, right?
We can show that we have
the top portion, the bottom.
We can actually be able to kind of really
look at all the different parts here.
So, if I have the anatomy of the wave,
notice how the tops are all crests.
The bottoms are what we call trowels,
so the lowest portions of these.
But the most important part is the
distance between the two peaks.
So we have the distance between these two.
This is referred to as a wavelength,
which uses the symbol lambda
to illustrate that difference.
Now, one of the things that I kind
of, as I was showing before, but it
was different on my, on my slides
versus my tablet, is how can we
describe how these waves are moving?
So up here I found a, a gif of
traditional waves and light waves.
The one above is essentially
how you picture waves if
you go to the beach, right?
Waves are oscillating,
they're coming at you.
You can stand in the water and you'll keep
getting hit by that top part of that wave.
So the top part, that is your crest.
So all the ones that are kind of
going up here, I know it's pausing,
are your crest at the top portion.
That's the part that's knocking you back.
There's a ton of energy that's
associated with that point.
as it hits you.
Now, there's a distance between those
crests, and the other portion is all about
how often does that crest hit you, right?
So as it's oscillating, you're also
going to have a frequency of how
often that is hitting you as well.
So the speed of light is always equal, is
essentially related to the wavelength and
the frequency of how often it's hitting.
Let's take a look a little bit farther
about how this works and how we can try
to understand this idea of frequency.
Frequency is essentially, we represent
this by the Greek letter nu, which looks
like, it looks very similar to a V,
but it's a little tiny bit different.
Um, so just to kind of illustrate that
to write it here, essentially if I would
kind of put a little curve on the V here.
This is a new.
All right.
So there's a little, it
looks slightly different.
I know it's subtle and you're
like, it looks the same, but
I promise you it's different.
So, um, with that, with that frequency,
that's essentially an inverse seconds
because we're curious about how often
it's hitting the starting point.
So imagine you standing
in the, at the beach.
Standing in the middle of the water,
how often are the waves hitting you?
So, one way to kind of think about
it is, um, as we're kind of moving
forward, is, we'll try to talk about
the relationships and I'll use some
analogies to try to make that make sense.
With waves, right, they can
also come in different forms.
How strong are they?
How are the wavelengths being affected?
Um, a few things is like
how dim or how bright it is.
Remember, we're talking about light.
So if you have like a dimmer switch at
home, making your lights really, really
bright or really, really dim, essentially
the wave will grow or shrink in height.
So if it's a very, very bright
light, it's going to have a very
tall wave versus if it's very
dim, it's going to be very short.
So this is the amplitude or
how strong or how big it is.
Um, we also have wavelengths can
change now based on the size of the
wave, whether it's really short or
if it's really long can change the
color that you perceive as well within
the visible portion of the spectrum.
So this is also something that we're going
to be discussing quite a bit as well.
So now, one of the things about
as we kind of go through this.
We need to be able to understand
what the relationship is between
wavelength and frequency.
How can we show that?
Well, it's actually a little bit simpler,
or sort of simple, how to explain it.
So, if you're standing at the beach, and
you have a wave hitting you over time.
Well, that wave has a
very specific wavelength.
And it is essentially going to be
hitting you at a very specific frequency.
What exactly are those units behind those?
Well, if you remember,
wavelength is a distance, right?
It's all about, if I have a
wave, is how far, essentially,
the tops of the different waves
are from each other, right?
So if I kind of draw that wave again, and
it keeps going, it's all about how far.
So that's meters.
Now, the new, or the inverse, or
the frequency is inverse seconds.
So what happens if I
were to times those two?
That's going to be meters per second.
But what was meters per second?
That was your speed of light.
So what does that tell you about
these two things, is what's important,
is there's a relationship here.
And essentially, as the wavelength
increases, the frequency will decrease.
Or vice versa, okay?
Now, how can I try to
explain that relationship?
So let's go back to the beach example,
probably where a lot of us would rather
be, rather than listening to this.
But how, how would we describe it?
Well, if you're standing at
the beach, you have waves
hitting you at such a frequency.
Now, compare that to, let's say, if
there was a hurricane or a storm.
How often do you think those
waves would be hitting you?
They'd be hitting you at a
very, very fast rate, right?
But, essentially, the distance between
those waves would be very, very short.
So, the waves up here could be like a
very calm day, versus if it's a hurricane,
you'll see that they are, or a storm,
the waves would be a lot closer together,
but the frequency is a lot greater.
So, notice how the frequency,
the wavelength is lower,
but the frequency increases.
Whereas here the wavelength increases
and the frequency decreases.
There is a relationship or how often
is it going to be hitting you as
the person standing on the beach.
Okay, so how often will that be hitting
you as it's traveling towards you?
That's kind of the idea.
All right, let's take a look a little
at a little bit more about this
type of how light and waves behave.
We have all the, we have the
wavelengths of these and the thing
is we measure them in meters.
Now, the range of this can vary immensely.
It goes from everywhere from 10 to the
negative 15 meters, which is around a
femtometer, to all the way down to 10 to
the 5, which is more around maybe like
a little bit over kilometers or even
close to megameters, so very, very large.
Now, these waves you can, they are
separated into different regions, so you
have radio waves, so what you listen to
possibly in your car, microwaves, how you
heat up food, infrared, if you kind of
have a heat lamp, or even just like an
infrared like heater at home, ultraviolet
from what the sun emits, x rays for
what we use in the medical field, and
gamma rays what we use for chemotherapy.
We have many different kinds of radiation
and they all spread at these different
areas now with that being said There
is a relationship here So the first
thing is where does the visible come in?
The visible is that tiny little
rainbow strip that's right there
in the middle of this slide, right?
So it's buried between
infrared and ultraviolet.
It's a very slim region between
400 nanometers and 750 nanometers.
So 10 to the negative nine meters.
We only see a very little or 10 negative
seven, 10, they have eight meters.
We only see a very very
tiny region of that.
So the thing about this is there's
a relationships as well is that the
smaller the wavelength, so going all
the way to let's say gamma rays, higher
the energy so the more powerful it is.
So very high frequencies
have very high energy.
So gamma and x rays are things
that can destroy things.
versus radio waves.
They don't interact with anything.
They're too low in energy.
This is why gamma rays are something that,
uh, when astronauts go into space, they
have to wear all the space protection,
not just for the oxygen, but to protect
them from radiation as well, because
ops and spaces and only gamma rays up
there mainly are the biggest threat.
Or when we're trying to radiate,
or try to radiate someone with
cancer, we'll generally use small
dosages of gamma rays to try to
target cancer cells to destroy that.
So, versus a radio wave, it's
something that just carries sound
and noise and something that won't be
anything that could be problematic.
There are relationships there, which
are very, very, very important.
Moving forward though, so we have that
relationship, we also have energy.
So I mentioned earlier that
every single wave carries energy.
How does it do that?
Well, this is where, um, it gets, can
get a little complicated, but being
this is just an introductory video,
uh, electromagnetic radiation or
waves have a wave particle duality to
them, meaning that they move as waves,
but they are also particles as well.
So these particles, they carry energy.
These particles are known as photons.
You probably have heard
of the word photon before.
Maybe if you've ever seen Star
Trek, the word photon torpedo is
used quite often in that show.
Um, it's also used in all kinds of
different science shows as well.
So essentially, energy is
equal to h times the frequency.
H is a constant, which you can find
on your handouts, um, which is 6.
626 times 10 to the negative 34.
If you times that by the frequency, you
will get your energy in joules, which
is just the letter J for the unit.
So not, not like the vape pen,
but joules, J O U L E S is how you
spell that, which will allow you to
be able to describe and to derive.
This can also be directly related
to wavelength as well, so if you
know that C is equal to lambda.
New, we could also show that we can
rearrange both of these formulas to show
that energy is equal to h times speed
of light divided by lambda as well.
It's all related to each other.
So all three of these formulas are formats
I'd write down in your notebook so that
way you have them for yourself when
you're trying to work up and use these.
And it's just a plug and play equation.
You put in your frequency, you put in
your wavelength, you can get your energy
and calculate all the different values.
Um, now, just to summarize all that,
the big thing is, is that wavelength
and frequency are interrelatable, right?
So as one goes up, the
other one goes down.
Amplitude is just how
big the wave is, right?
So how intense is it?
Um, and now, being that we have that
inverse relationship, it, uh, between
wavelength and frequency, is also
related to the energy as well, and that
all waves move at the speed of light.
So that is really some of the basic ideas
and we're going to be seeing a lot of this
kind of moving forward and how this works.
Now, why is it that
we're talking about this?
Why do we need to know?
Well, it has to do with quantum mechanics,
which when you hear that, you're like,
oh my god, what did I sign up for?
What am I trying to learn here?
I'm cutting this video into two parts,
so please look out for that part two.
Um, the whole idea here is I want
to be able to separate the quantum
mechanics portion of this video being
that it goes through the idea that
we need to, uh, that all electrons,
they need to go in their own specific
energy levels, which will eventually
go into their own individual orbitals.
Um, so this is a method for us to be
able to see that all electrons require
a certain amount of energy to excite
them, which will put them in their own
little essentially filing organization,
which is known as electron configuration.
So in the followup video, take
a look, look out for that.
It's going to be all on how quantum
really, uh, the basic idea of how
quantum works in a 15 minute video.
So thank you so much for watching
and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.